{"author": "Robert R. Harr","data": [{"chapter": "4.5","questions": [{"data": [{"choices": ["Compatibility testing must be performed before blood is issued","Compatibility testing will be performed when a patient sample is available","Compatibility testing may be performed immediately by using donor serum","Compatibility testing is not necessary when blood is issued in emergency situations"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Compatibility testing will be performed when a patient sample is available","explanation": "When patient serum is available, it will be crossmatched with donor cells. Patient serum might contain antibodies against antigens on donor cells that may destroy donor cells. If an incompatibility is discovered, the problem will be reported immediately to the patient’s physician."},"question": "SITUATION: An emergency trauma patient requires transfusion. Six units of blood are ordered stat (immediately). There is no time to draw a patient sample. O-negative blood is issued. When will compatibility testing be performed?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of laboratory operations/Crossmatch/3"},{"choices": ["No effect","The DAT result would be positive","ABO, Rh, antibody screen, and crossmatching may show abnormal results","Results would depend on the specificity of autoantibody"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "ABO, Rh, antibody screen, and crossmatching may show abnormal results","explanation": "Autoantibodies may cause positive reactions with screening cells, panel cells, donor cells, and patient cells. The DAT result will be positive; however, DAT is not included in compatibility testing."},"question": "How would autoantibodies affect compatibility testing?","reference": "Blood bank/Evaluate laboratory data to make identifications/Antibody ID/3"},{"choices": ["A cold alloantibody","High-frequency alloantibody or a mixture of alloantibodies","A warm autoantibody","A cold and warm alloantibody"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "High-frequency alloantibody or a mixture of alloantibodies","explanation": "High-frequency alloantibodies or a mixture of alloantibodies may cause all three screening cells to be positive. A negative autocontrol would rule out autoantibodies."},"question": "An antibody screen is reactive at the IAT phase of testing with all three cells of a three- cell screen, and the autocontrol is negative. What is a possible explanation for these results?","reference": "Blood bank/Evaluate laboratory data to make identifications/Antibody ID/3"},{"choices": ["Recipient plasma and recipient RBCs","Recipient plasma and donor RBCs","Recipient RBCs and donor plasma","Donor plasma and donor RBCs"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Recipient RBCs and donor plasma","explanation": "A minor crossmatch consists of recipient RBCs and donor serum or plasma."},"question": "What does a minor crossmatch consist of?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of laboratory operations/Crossmatch/1"},{"choices": ["Yes, a new sample would not be needed","Yes, but only if the previous sample has no alloantibodies","No, a new sample is needed because the 2-day limit has expired","No, a new sample is needed for each testing"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Yes, a new sample would not be needed","explanation": "Compatibility testing may be performed on a patient sample within 3 days of the scheduled transfusion; however, if the patient is pregnant or was transfused within 3 months, the sample must be less than 3 days old."},"question": "Can crossmatching be performed on October 14 using a patient sample drawn on October 12?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Crossmatch/2"},{"choices": ["Order AB-negative units from a blood supplier","Check inventory of A-, B-, and O-negative units","Ask the patient to make a preoperative autologous donation","Nothing—the blood will probably not be used"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Check inventory of A-, B-, and O-negative units","explanation": "An AB person is the universal recipient and may receive any blood type; because only a type and screen were ordered and blood may not be used, check inventory for A-, B-, and O-negative units."},"question": "A type and screen was performed on a 32-year-old woman, and the patient was typed as AB negative. There are no AB-negative units in the blood bank. What should be done?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of basic laboratory procedures/Crossmatch/2"},{"choices": ["A negative, B negative, AB negative, O negative","O negative","AB negative","AB negative, A negative, B negative"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "O negative","explanation": "An O-negative individual has no A or B antigens and may donate RBCs to any other ABO type."},"question": "What ABO types may donate to any other ABO type?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Crossmatch/2"},{"choices": ["A negative, B negative, AB negative, or O negative","O negative","AB negative","AB negative, A negative, B negative"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "O negative","explanation": "An O-negative individual has both anti-A and anti-B and may receive only O-negative RBCs."},"question": "What type(s) of RBC(s) is (are) acceptable to transfuse to an O-negative patient?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Crossmatch/2"},{"choices": ["Issue the unit if the RBCs appear normal","Reseal the unit","Discard the unit","Call the medical director and ask for an opinion"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Discard the unit","explanation": "Leaking may indicate a broken seal or a puncture, which indicates possible contamination of the unit, even if the RBCs appear normal. The unit should be discarded."},"question": "An MLS removed 4 units of blood from the blood bank refrigerator and placed them on the counter. A clerk was waiting to take the units for transfusion. As she checked the paperwork, she noticed that one of the units was leaking onto the counter. What should she do?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of standard operating procedures/Crossmatch/3"},{"choices": ["The AHG major crossmatch would be positive","The IS major crossmatch would be positive","The recipient’s antibody screen would be positive for anti-K","Compatibility testing would not be affected"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Compatibility testing would not be affected","explanation": "Compatibility testing would not be affected if the donor has anti-K in his or her serum. This is because the major crossmatch uses recipient serum and not donor serum. Other tests, such as ABO, Rh, and antibody screen on the recipient, also would not be affected."},"question": "A donor was found to contain anti-K using pilot tubes from the collection procedure. How would this affect the compatibility test?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of basic laboratory procedures/Crossmatch/2"},{"choices": ["The computer system contains logic to prevent assignment and release of ABO- incompatible blood","There are concordant results of at least two determinations of the recipient’s ABO type on record, one of which is from the current sample","Critical elements of the system have been validated on site","There are concordant results of at least one determination of the recipient’s ABO type on file"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "There are concordant results of at least one determination of the recipient’s ABO type on file","explanation": "ABO determinations must be concordant on at least two occasions, including the current sample."},"question": "Which of the following is not a requirement for electronic crossmatching?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of basic laboratory procedures/Crossmatch/1"},{"choices": ["Anti-H", "Anti-S", "Anti-Kpa", "Anti-k"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Anti-k","explanation": "Anti-k (Cellano) is a high-frequency alloantibody that would react with screening cells and most donor units. The negative autocontrol rules out autoantibodies. Anti-H and anti-S are cold antibodies and anti-Kpa is a low-frequency alloantibody."},"question": "A patient showed positive results with screening cells and 4 donor units. The patient autocontrol was negative. What is the most likely antibody?","reference": "Blood bank/Evaluate laboratory data to make identifications/Incompatible crossmatch/3"},{"choices": ["Cold alloantibody","Cold autoantibody","Abnormal protein","Antibody mixture"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Cold alloantibody","explanation": "A cold alloantibody would show a reaction with screening cells and donor units only at the IS phase. The negative autocontrol rules out autoantibodies and abnormal protein."},"question": "Screening cells and major crossmatch are positive on IS only, and the autocontrol is negative. Identify the problem.","reference": "Blood bank/Evaluate laboratory data to make identifications/Incompatible crossmatch/3"},{"choices": ["Patient may have an alloantibody to a high-frequency antigen","Patient may have an abnormal protein","Donor unit may have a positive DAT","Donor may have a high-frequency antigen"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Donor unit may have a positive DAT","explanation": "The incompatible donor unit may have an antibody coating the RBCs, or the patient may have an alloantibody to a low-frequency antigen. An alloantibody to a high-frequency antigen would agglutinate all units and screening cells."},"question": "Six units are crossmatched. Five units are compatible, one unit is incompatible, and the recipient’s antibody screen is negative. Identify the problem:","reference": "Blood bank/Evaluate laboratory data to make identifications/Incompatible crossmatch/3"},{"choices": ["Discard the unit","Antigen type the unit for high-frequency antigens","Wash the donor cells and use the washed cells for testing","Perform a panel on the incompatible unit"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Discard the unit","explanation": "The incompatible unit may have RBCs coated with antibody and/or complement. If RBCs are sensitized, then some problem exists with the donor. Discard the unit."},"question": "An incompatible donor unit is found to have a positive result on DAT. What should be done with the donor unit?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of special procedures/Incompatible crossmatch/3"},{"choices": ["Specific cold alloantibody","Specific cold autoantibody","Abnormal protein or nonspecific autoantibody","Cold and warm alloantibody mixture"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Abnormal protein or nonspecific autoantibody","explanation": "An abnormal protein or nonspecific autoantibody would cause antibody screen, crossmatch, and patient autocontrol to be positive. Alloantibodies would not cause a positive patient autocontrol."},"question": "Screening cells, major crossmatch, and patient autocontrol are positive in all phases. Identify the problem.","reference": "Blood bank/Evaluate laboratory data to make identifications/Incompatible crossmatch/3"},{"choices": ["Perform a DAT on patient cells and donor units","Antigen type patient cells and any donor cells to be crossmatched","Adsorb any antibodies from patient serum","Obtain a different enhancement medium for testing"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Antigen type patient cells and any donor cells to be crossmatched","explanation": "Antigen typing or phenotyping of the patient’s cells confirms the antibody identification; antigen typing of donor cells helps ensure the crossmatch of compatible donor units."},"question": "A panel study has revealed the presence of patient alloantibodies. What is the first step in a major crossmatch?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of special procedures/Incompatible crossmatch/2"},{"choices": ["The unit must be discarded","Only the plasma may be used to make components","The antibody must be adsorbed from the unit","The unit may be labeled to indicate that it contains antibody and released into inventory"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "The unit may be labeled to indicate that it contains antibody and released into inventory","explanation": "The unit may be used in the general blood inventory, if it is properly labeled and only cellular elements are used."},"question": "What is the disposition of a donor RBC unit that contains an antibody?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of laboratory operations/Hemotherapy/Blood components/1"},{"choices": ["Adsorption using rabbit stroma","Antigen typing of patient cells","Elution followed by a cell panel on the eluate","Selected cell panel"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Elution followed by a cell panel on the eluate","explanation": "A positive DAT using anti-IgG indicates that antibodies are coating the patient’s cells. An eluate would be helpful to remove the antibody, followed by a cell panel to identify it."},"question": "Given a situation where screening cells, major crossmatch, autocontrol, and DAT (anti- IgG) are all positive, what procedure should be performed next?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of special procedures/Incompatible crossmatch/3"},{"choices": ["Combination of antibodies","Cold alloantibody","Rouleaux","Test error"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Cold alloantibody","explanation": "The reaction pattern fits that of a cold antibody reacting at the IS phase and of sufficient titer to persist at 37°C incubation. The reactions disappear in the IAT phase."},"question": "A major crossmatch and screening cells are 2+ at the IS phase, 1+ at 37°C, and negative at the IAT phase. Identify the most likely problem.","reference": "Blood bank/Evaluate laboratory data to make identifications/Incompatible crossmatch/3"},{"choices": ["Perform a saline replacement technique","Perform an autoabsorption","Run a panel","Perform an elution"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Perform a saline replacement technique","explanation": "Rouleaux may be dispersed or lessened by using the saline replacement technique. This involves recentrifuging the tube, then withdrawing serum and replacing it with two drops of saline. The tube is respun and examined for hemolysis."},"question": "What corrective action should be taken when rouleaux causes positive test results?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of special procedures/Testing problems/3"},{"choices": ["Separation of mixtures of antibodies","Removal of interfering substances","Confirmation of weak antigens on RBCs","Identification of antibodies causing a positive DAT"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Identification of antibodies causing a positive DAT","explanation": "Antibodies causing a positive DAT would be coating RBCs and would require elution, not adsorption, to identify them."},"question": "All of the following are reasons for performing an adsorption, except:","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of special procedures/Antibody identification/2"},{"choices": ["3 days", "5 days", "7 days", "10 days"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "7 days","explanation": "According to the American Association of Blood Banks (AABB) standards, the recipient sample must be kept for 7 days after compatibility testing."},"question": "How long must a recipient sample be kept in the blood bank after compatibility testing?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of basic laboratory procedures/Compatibility/1"},{"choices": ["Perform a reverse grouping on donor plasma","No testing is required","Perform a reverse grouping on recipient plasma","Platelets must be HLA compatible"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "No testing is required","explanation": "For transfusion of platelets and plasma, there is no required protocol for crossmatching."},"question": "What is the crossmatching protocol for platelets and/or plasma?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of basic laboratory procedures/Compatibility/2"},{"choices": ["ABO and Rh typing","Type and screen","Major crossmatch","All of these options"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "ABO and Rh typing","explanation": "The only requirement for transfusing an autologous unit is a check of the ABO and Rh types."},"question": "What are the compatibility requirements for an autologous unit?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of basic laboratory procedures/Compatibility/1"},{"choices": ["A-positive units","O-positive units","B-positive units","Call another blood supplier for type-specific blood"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "A-positive units","explanation": "The type chosen should be A-positive RBC units. Although all choices would be compatible, the first choice should be A-positive because this unit will contain residual plasma anti-B. Anti-B is less immunogenic than anti-A, which would be present, albeit in small amounts, in B-positive and O-positive units."},"question": "A patient is typed as AB positive. Two units of blood have been ordered by the physician. Currently, the inventory shows no AB units, 10 A-positive units, 1 A-negative unit, 5 B-positive units, and 20 O-positive units. Which should be set up for the major crossmatch?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of basic laboratory procedures/Compatibility/2"},{"choices": ["ABO, Rh, and antibody screen","ABO, Rh, antibody screen, IS crossmatch","Type and screen","ABO, Rh, IS crossmatch"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "ABO, Rh, antibody screen, IS crossmatch","explanation": "The abbreviated crossmatch usually consists of a type and screen and an IS crossmatch."},"question": "Which of the following comprises an abbreviated crossmatch?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of basic laboratory procedures/Crossmatch/2"},{"choices": ["When a patient is being massively transfused","When there is no history of antibodies and the current antibody screen is negative","When blood is being emergency released","When a patient has not been transfused in the past 3 months"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "When there is no history of antibodies and the current antibody screen is negative","explanation": "IS crossmatching may be performed when the patient has no history of antibodies and the current antibody screen is negative."},"question": "When may IS crossmatching be performed?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of basic laboratory procedures/Crossmatch/1"}],"type": "MULTIPLE_CHOICE"}],"topic": "Compatibility Testing"}],"edition": "5th","title": "Medical Laboratory Science Review"}